Number Series
[{"question": "Look at this series: 2, 1, (1/2), (1/4), ... What number should come next?", "options": ["(1/3)", "(1/8)", "(2/8)", "(1/16)"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 7, 10, 8, 11, 9, 12, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["7", "10", "12", "13"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 36, 34, 30, 28, 24, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["20", "22", "23", "26"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 22, 21, 23, 22, 24, 23, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["22", "24", "25", "26"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 53, 53, 40, 40, 27, 27, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["12", "14", "27", "53"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 21, 9, 21, 11, 21, 13, 21, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["14", "15", "21", "23"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 58, 52, 46, 40, 34, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["26", "28", "30", "32"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 3, 4, 7, 8, 11, 12, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["7", "10", "14", "15"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 8, 22, 8, 28, 8, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["9", "29", "32", "34"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 31, 29, 24, 22, 17, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["15", "14", "13", "12"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 1.5, 2.3, 3.1, 3.9, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["4.2", "4.4", "4.7", "5.1"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 14, 28, 20, 40, 32, 64, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["52", "56", "96", "128"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["11", "12", "13", "14"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 201, 202, 204, 207, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["205", "208", "210", "211"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 544, 509, 474, 439, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["404", "414", "420", "445"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 80, 10, 70, 15, 60, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["20", "25", "30", "50"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 2, 6, 18, 54, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["108", "148", "162", "216"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 5.2, 4.8, 4.4, 4, ... What number should come next?", "options": ["3", "3.3", "3.5", "3.6"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Look at this series: 8, 6, 9, 23, 87 , ... What number should come next?", "options": ["128", "226", "324", "429"], "answer": "d"}]

Letter and Symbol Series
[{"question": "SCD, TEF, UGH, ____, WKL", "options": ["CMN", "UJI", "VIJ", "IJT"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "B2CD, _____, BCD4, B5CD, BC6D", "options": ["B2C2D", "BC3D", "B2C3D", "BCD7"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "FAG, GAF, HAI, IAH, ____", "options": ["JAK", "HAL", "HAK", "JAI"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "ELFA, GLHA, ILJA, _____, MLNA", "options": ["OLPA", "KLMA", "LLMA", "KLLA"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "CMM, EOO, GQQ, _____, KUU", "options": ["GRR", "GSS", "ISS", "ITT"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "ZA5, Y4B, XC6, W3D, _____", "options": ["E7V", "V2E", "VE5", "VE7"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "QPO, NML, KJI, _____, EDC", "options": ["HGF", "CAB", "JKL", "GHI"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "JAK, KBL, LCM, MDN, _____", "options": ["OEP", "NEO", "MEN", "PFQ"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "BCB, DED, FGF, HIH, ___", "options": ["JKJ", "HJH", "IJI", "JHJ"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "P5QR, P4QS, P3QT, _____, P1QV", "options": ["PQW", "PQV2", "P2QU", "PQ3U"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "QAR, RAS, SAT, TAU, _____", "options": ["UAV", "UAT", "TAS", "TAT"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "DEF, DEF2, DE2F2, _____, D2E2F3", "options": ["DEF3", "D3EF3", "D2E3F", "D2E2F2"], "answer": "d"}]

Verbal Classification
[{"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["parsley", "basil", "dill", "mayonnaise"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["inch", "ounce", "centimeter", "yard"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["tyre", "steering wheel", "engine", "car"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["tulip", "rose", "bud", "daisy"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["rye", "sourdough", "pumpernickel", "loaf"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["guitar", "flute", "violin", "cello"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["dodge", "flee", "duck", "avoid"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["branch", "dirt", "leaf", "root"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["street", "freeway", "interstate", "expressway"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["heading", "body", "letter", "closing"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["tape", "twine", "cord", "yarn"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["leopard", "cougar", "elephant", "lion"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["couch", "rug", "table", "chair"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["cornea", "retina", "pupil", "vision"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["noun", "preposition", "punctuation", "adverb"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["book", "index", "glossary", "chapter"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Which word does NOT belong with the others?", "options": ["unimportant", "trivial", "insignificant", "familiar"], "answer": "d"}]

Essential Part
[{"question": "harvest", "options": ["autumn", "stockpile", "tractor", "crop"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "desert", "options": ["cactus", "arid", "oasis", "flat"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "book", "options": ["fiction", "pages", "pictures", "learning"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "language", "options": ["tongue", "slang", "writing", "words"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "school", "options": ["student", "report card", "test", "learning"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "pain", "options": ["cut", "burn", "nuisance", "hurt"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "gala", "options": ["celebration", "tuxedo", "appetizer", "orator"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "monopoly", "options": ["corrupt", "exclusive", "rich", "gigantic"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "guitar", "options": ["band", "teacher", "songs", "strings"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "election", "options": ["president", "voter", "November", "nation"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "shoe", "options": ["sole", "leather", "laces", "walking"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "swimming", "options": ["pool", "bathing suit", "water", "life jacket"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "lightning", "options": ["electricity", "thunder", "brightness", "rain"], "answer": "a"}]

Analogies
[{"question": "Odometer is to mileage as compass is to", "options": ["speed", "hiking", "needle", "direction"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Marathon is to race as hibernation is to", "options": ["winter", "bear", "dream", "sleep"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Window is to pane as book is to", "options": ["novel", "glass", "cover", "page"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Cup is to coffee as bowl is to", "options": ["dish", "soup", "spoon", "food"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Yard is to inch as quart is to", "options": ["gallon", "ounce", "milk", "liquid"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Elated is to despondent as enlightened is to", "options": ["aware", "ignorant", "miserable", "tolerant"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Optimist is to cheerful as pessimist is to", "options": ["gloomy", "mean", "petty", "helpful"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Reptile is to lizard as flower is to", "options": ["petal", "stem", "daisy", "alligator"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Play is to actor as concert is to", "options": ["symphony", "musician", "piano", "percussion"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Sponge is to porous as rubber is to", "options": ["massive", "solid", "elastic", "inflexible"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Careful is to cautious as boastful is to", "options": ["arrogant", "humble", "joyful", "suspicious"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Pen is to poet as needle is to", "options": ["thread", "button", "sewing", "tailor"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Secretly is to openly as silently is to", "options": ["scarcely", "impolitely", "noisily", "quietly"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Embarrassed is to humiliated as frightened is to", "options": ["terrified", "agitated", "courageous", "reckless"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Pride is to lion as shoal is to", "options": ["teacher", "student", "self-respect", "fish"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Artist is to painting as senator is to", "options": ["attorney", "law", "politician", "constituents"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Exercise is to gym as eating is to", "options": ["food", "dieting", "fitness", "restaurant"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Candid is to indirect as honest is to", "options": ["frank", "wicked", "truthful", "untruthful"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Guide is to direct as reduce is to", "options": ["decrease", "maintain", "increase", "preserve"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Oar is to rowboat as foot is to", "options": ["running", "sneaker", "skateboard", "jumping"], "answer": "c"}]

Artificial Language
[{"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ngorblflur means fan belt\npixngorbl means ceiling fan\narthtusl means tile roof\nWhich word could mean "ceiling tile"?", "options": ["gorbltusl", "flurgorbl", "arthflur", "pixnarth"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nhapllesh means cloudburst\nsrenchoch means pinball\nresbosrench means ninepin\nWhich word could mean "cloud nine"?", "options": ["leshsrench", "ochhapl", "haploch", "haplresbo"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nagnoscrenia means poisonous spider\ndelanocrenia means poisonous snake\nagnosdeery means brown spider\nWhich word could mean "black widow spider"?", "options": ["deeryclostagnos", "agnosdelano", "agnosvitriblunin", "trymuttiagnos"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nmoolokarn means blue sky\nwilkospadi means bicycle race\nmoolowilko means blue bicycle\nWhich word could mean "racecar"?", "options": ["wilkozwet", "spadiwilko", "moolobreil", "spadivolo"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nmigenlasan means cupboard\nlasanpoen means boardwalk\ncuopdansa means pullman\nWhich word could mean "walkway"?", "options": ["poenmigen", "cuopeisel", "lasandansa", "poenforc"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ngodabim means kidney stones\nromzbim means kidney beans\nromzbako means wax beans\nWhich word could mean "wax statue"?", "options": ["godaromz", "lazbim", "wasibako", "romzpeo"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ngranamelke means big tree\npinimelke means little tree\nmelkehoon means tree house\nWhich word could mean "big house"?", "options": ["granahoon", "pinishur", "pinihoon", "melkegrana"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ndaftafoni means advisement\nimodafta means misadvise\nimolokti means misconduct\nWhich word could mean "statement"?", "options": ["kratafoni", "kratadafta", "loktifoni", "daftaimo"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nlelibroon means yellow hat\nplekafroti means flower garden\nfrotimix means garden salad\nWhich word could mean "yellow flower"?", "options": ["lelifroti", "lelipleka", "plekabroon", "frotibroon"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nmyncabel means saddle horse\nconowir means trail ride\ncabelalma means horse blanket\nWhich word could mean "horse ride"?", "options": ["cabelwir", "conocabel", "almamyn", "conoalma"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ndionot means oak tree\nblyonot means oak leaf\nblycrin means maple leaf\nWhich word could mean "maple syrup"?", "options": ["blymuth", "hupponot", "patricrin", "crinweel"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ntamceno means sky blue\ncenorax means blue cheese\naplmitl means star bright\nWhich word could mean "bright sky"?", "options": ["cenotam", "mitltam", "raxmitl", "aplceno"], "answer": "b"}]

Matching Definitions
[{"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ngorblflur means fan belt\npixngorbl means ceiling fan\narthtusl means tile roof\nWhich word could mean "ceiling tile"?", "options": ["gorbltusl", "flurgorbl", "arthflur", "pixnarth"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nhapllesh means cloudburst\nsrenchoch means pinball\nresbosrench means ninepin\nWhich word could mean "cloud nine"?", "options": ["leshsrench", "ochhapl", "haploch", "haplresbo"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nagnoscrenia means poisonous spider\ndelanocrenia means poisonous snake\nagnosdeery means brown spider\nWhich word could mean "black widow spider"?", "options": ["deeryclostagnos", "agnosdelano", "agnosvitriblunin", "trymuttiagnos"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nmoolokarn means blue sky\nwilkospadi means bicycle race\nmoolowilko means blue bicycle\nWhich word could mean "racecar"?", "options": ["wilkozwet", "spadiwilko", "moolobreil", "spadivolo"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nmigenlasan means cupboard\nlasanpoen means boardwalk\ncuopdansa means pullman\nWhich word could mean "walkway"?", "options": ["poenmigen", "cuopeisel", "lasandansa", "poenforc"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ngodabim means kidney stones\nromzbim means kidney beans\nromzbako means wax beans\nWhich word could mean "wax statue"?", "options": ["godaromz", "lazbim", "wasibako", "romzpeo"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ngranamelke means big tree\npinimelke means little tree\nmelkehoon means tree house\nWhich word could mean "big house"?", "options": ["granahoon", "pinishur", "pinihoon", "melkegrana"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ndaftafoni means advisement\nimodafta means misadvise\nimolokti means misconduct\nWhich word could mean "statement"?", "options": ["kratafoni", "kratadafta", "loktifoni", "daftaimo"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nlelibroon means yellow hat\nplekafroti means flower garden\nfrotimix means garden salad\nWhich word could mean "yellow flower"?", "options": ["lelifroti", "lelipleka", "plekabroon", "frotibroon"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\nmyncabel means saddle horse\nconowir means trail ride\ncabelalma means horse blanket\nWhich word could mean "horse ride"?", "options": ["cabelwir", "conocabel", "almamyn", "conoalma"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ndionot means oak tree\nblyonot means oak leaf\nblycrin means maple leaf\nWhich word could mean "maple syrup"?", "options": ["blymuth", "hupponot", "patricrin", "crinweel"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Here are some words translated from an artificial language.\ntamceno means sky blue\ncenorax means blue cheese\naplmitl means star bright\nWhich word could mean "bright sky"?", "options": ["cenotam", "mitltam", "raxmitl", "aplceno"], "answer": "b"}]

Making Judgments
[{"question": "Eileen is planning a special birthday dinner for her husband"s 35th birthday. She wants the evening to be memorable, but her husband is a simple man who would rather be in jeans at a baseball game than in a suit at a fancy restaurant. Which restaurant below should Eileen choose?", "options": ["Alfredo"s offers fine Italian cuisine and an elegant Tuscan decor. Patrons will feel as though they"ve spent the evening in a luxurious Italian villa.", "Pancho"s Mexican Buffet is an all-you-can-eat family style smorgasbord with the best tacos in town.", "The Parisian Bistro is a four-star French restaurant where guests are treated like royalty. Chef Dilbert Olay is famous for his beef bourguignon.", "Marty"s serves delicious, hearty meals in a charming setting reminiscent of a baseball clubhouse in honor of the owner,Marty Lester, a former major league baseball all-star."], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "The film director wants an actress for the lead role of Lucy who perfectly fits the description that appears in the original screenplay. He is not willing to consider actresses who do not resemble the character as she is described in the screenplay, no matter how talented they are. The screenplay describes Lucy as an average-sized, forty something redhead, with deep brown eyes, very fair skin, and a brilliant smile. The casting agent has four actresses in mind.\nActress #1 is a stunning red-haired beauty who is 5\"9" and in her mid-twenties. Her eyes are brown and she has an olive complexion.\nActress #2 has red hair, big brown eyes, and a fair complexion. She is in her mid-forties and is 5\"5".\nActress #3 is 5\"4" and of medium build. She has red hair, brown eyes, and is in her early forties.\nActress #4 is a blue-eyed redhead in her early thirties. She\"s of very slight build and stands at 5\".", "options": ["1, 2", "2, 3", "1, 4", "2, 4"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "The school principal has received complaints from parents about bullying in the school yard during recess. He wants to investigate and end this situation as soon as possible, so he has asked the recess aides to watch closely. Which situation should the recess aides report to the principal?", "options": ["A girl is sitting glumly on a bench reading a book and not interacting with her peers.", "Four girls are surrounding another girl and seem to have possession of her backpack.", "Two boys are playing a one-on-one game of basketball and are arguing over the last basket scored.", "Three boys are huddled over a handheld video game, which isn"t supposed to be on school grounds."], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Mrs. Carson took a taxi to meet her three friends for lunch. They were waiting for her outside the restaurant when she pulled up in the car. She was so excited to see her friends that she left her tote bag in the taxi. As the taxi pulled away, she and her friends took notice of the license plate number so they would be able to identify the car when they called the taxi company.\n#1: The four women seem to agree that the plate starts out with the letter J.\n#2: Three of them agree that the plate ends with 12L.\n#3: Three of them think that the second letter is X, and a different three think that the third letter is K.\nThe four license plate numbers below represent what each of the four women thinks she saw. Which one is most likely the license plate number of the taxi?", "options": ["JXK 12L", "JYK 12L", "JXK 12I", "JXX 12L"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Zachary has invited his three buddies over to watch the basketball game on his wide-screen television. They are all hungry, but no one wants to leave to get food. Just as they are arguing about who should make the food run, a commercial comes on for a local pizze-ria that delivers. The phone number flashes on the screen briefly and they all try to remember it. By the time Zachary grabs a pen and paper, each of them recollects a different number.\n#1: All of the men agree that the first three numbers are 995.\n#2: Three of them agree that the fourth number is 9.\n#3: Three agree that the fifth number is 2.\n#4: Three agree that the sixth number is 6; three others agree that the seventh number is also 6.\nWhich of the numbers is most likely the telephone number of the pizzeria?", "options": ["995-9266", "995-9336", "995-9268", "995-8266"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Mark is working with a realtor to find a location for the toy store he plans to open in his town. He is looking for a place that is either in, or not too far from, the center of town and one that would attract the right kind of foot traffic. Which of the following locations should Mark"s realtor call to his attention?", "options": ["a storefront in a new high-rise building near the train station in the center of town whose occupants are mainly young, childless professionals who use the train to commute to their offices each day.", "a little shop three blocks away from the town"s main street, located across the street from an elementary school and next door to an ice cream store", "a stand-alone storefront on a quiet residential street ten blocks away from the town"s center", "a storefront in a small strip mall located on the outskirts of town that is also occupied by a pharmacy and a dry cleaner"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "The neighborhood block association has received many complaints about people knocking on doors and soliciting money for an unknown charity organization even though door-to-door solicitation is prohibited by local laws. Three residents have provided descriptions of individuals who have come to their door asking for money.\nSolicitor #1 is a white male, 20-25 years old, 5\"9", 145 pounds, with very short brown hair. He was wearing a dark blue suit and carrying a brown leather briefcase.\nSolicitor #2 is a white male, 25-30 years old, 6\"2", 200 pounds, with a shaved-head. He was wearing a red T-shirt and jeans.\nSolicitor #3 is a white male, approximately 23 years old, 5\"10", slight build, with short brown hair. He was wearing a blue suit.\nThree days after the block association meet- ing, a resident noticed a man knocking on doors in the neighborhood and phoned the police to report the illegal activity. This solic- itor was described as follows:\nSolicitor #4 is a white male, 22 years old, 140 pounds, about 5\"10", with short brown hair. He was carrying a briefcase and wearing a dark suit.\nBased on this description, which of the three solicitations was also likely carried out by Solicitor #4?", "options": ["#1, #2, and #3", "#1, but not #2 and #3", "#1 and #3, but not #2", "#1 and #2, but not #3"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Rita, an accomplished pastry chef who is well known for her artistic and exquisite wedding cakes, opened a bakery one year ago and is surprised that business has been so slow. A consultant she hired to conduct market research has reported that the local population doesn"t think of her shop as one they would visit on a daily basis but rather a place they"d visit if they were celebrating a special occasion. Which of the following strategies should Rita employ to increase her daily business?", "options": ["making coupons available that entitle the coupon holder to receive a 25% discount on wedding, anniversary, or birthday cakes", "exhibiting at the next Bridal Expo and having pieces of one of her wedding cakes available for tasting", "placing a series of ads in the local newspaper that advertise the wide array of breads", "moving the bakery to the other side of town"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Dr. Miller has a busy pediatric dentistry practice and she needs a skilled, reliable hygienist to keep things running smoothly. The last two people she hired were recommended by top dentists in the area, but they each lasted less than one month. She is now in desperate need of a hygienist who can competently handle the specific challenges of her practice. Which one of the following candidates should Dr. Miller consider most seriously?", "options": ["Marilyn has been a hygienist for fifteen years, and her current employer, who is about to retire, says she is the best in the business. The clientele she has worked with consists of some of the wealthiest and most powerful citizens in the county.", "Lindy recently graduated at the top of her class from one of the best dental hygiene programs in the state. Prior to becoming a dental hygienist, Lindy spent two years working in a day care center.", "James has worked as a dental hygienist for three years in a public health clinic. He is very interested in securing a position in a private dental office.", "Kathy is an experienced and highly recommended dental hygienist who is also finishing up a degree in early childhood education, which she hopes will get her a job as a preschool teacher. She is eager to find a job in a pediatric practice, since she has always wanted to work with children."], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Mrs. Jansen recently moved to Arizona. She wants to fill her new backyard with flowering plants. Although she is an experienced gardener, she isn"t very well-versed in what plants will do well in the Arizona climate. Also, there is a big tree in her backyard making for shady conditions and she isn"t sure what plants will thrive without much direct sunlight. Her favorite gardening catalog offers several backyard seed packages. Which one should Mrs. Jansen choose?", "options": ["The Rainbow Collection is ideal for North-east gardens. It includes a variety of colorful perennials that thrive in cool, moist conditions.", "The Greenhouse Collection will blossom year after year if planted in brightly lit locations and watered regularly.", "The Treehouse Collection will provide lush green plants with delicate colorful flowers that thrive in shady and partially shady locations.", "The Oasis Collection includes a variety of perennials that thrive in dry climates and bright sunlight."], "answer": "c"}]

Verbal Reasoning
[{"question": "Vincent has a paper route. Each morning, he delivers 37 newspapers to customers in his neighborhood. It takes Vincent 50 minutes to deliver all the papers. If Vincent is sick or has other plans, his friend Thomas, who lives on the same street, will sometimes deliver the papers for him.", "options": ["Vincent and Thomas live in the same neighborhood.", "It takes Thomas more than 50 minutes to deliver the papers.", "It is dark outside when Vincent begins his deliveries.", "Thomas would like to have his own paper route."], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "The Pacific yew is an evergreen tree that grows in the Pacific Northwest. The Pacific yew has a fleshy, poisonous fruit. Recently, taxol, a substance found in the bark of the Pacific yew, was discovered to be a promising new anticancer drug.", "options": ["Taxol is poisonous when taken by healthy people.", "Taxol has cured people from various diseases.", "People should not eat the fruit of the Pacific yew.", "The Pacific yew was considered worthless until taxol was discovered."], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Erin is twelve years old. For three years, she has been asking her parents for a dog. Her parents have told her that they believe a dog would not be happy in an apartment, but they have given her permission to have a bird. Erin has not yet decided what kind of bird she would like to have.", "options": ["Erin"s parents like birds better than they like dogs.", "Erin does not like birds.", "Erin and her parents live in an apartment.", "Erin and her parents would like to move."], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Tim"s commute never bothered him because there were always seats available on the train and he was able to spend his 40 minutes comfortably reading the newspaper or catching up on paperwork. Ever since the train schedule changed, the train has been extremely crowded, and by the time the doors open at his station, there isn"t a seat to be found.", "options": ["Tim would be better off taking the bus to work.", "Tim"s commute is less comfortable since the train schedule changed.", "Many commuters will complain about the new train schedule.", "Tim will likely look for a new job closer to home."], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "When they heard news of the hurricane, Maya and Julian decided to change their vacation plans. Instead of traveling to the island beach resort, they booked a room at a fancy new spa in the mountains. Their plans were a bit more expensive, but they"d heard wonderful things about the spa and they were relieved to find availability on such short notice.", "options": ["Maya and Julian take beach vacations every year.", "The spa is overpriced.", "It is usually necessary to book at least six months in advance at the spa.", "Maya and Julian decided to change their vacation plans because of the hurricane."], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Ten new television shows appeared during the month of September. Five of the shows were sitcoms, three were hour-long dramas, and two were news-magazine shows. By January, only seven of these new shows were still on the air. Five of the shows that remained were sitcoms.", "options": ["Only one of the news-magazine shows remained on the air.", "Only one of the hour-long dramas remained on the air.", "At least one of the shows that was cancelled was an hour-long drama.", "Television viewers prefer sitcoms over hour-long dramas."], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "On weekends, Mr. Sanchez spends many hours working in his vegetable and flower gardens. Mrs. Sanchez spends her free time reading and listening to classical music. Both Mr. Sanchez and Mrs. Sanchez like to cook.", "options": ["Mr. Sanchez enjoys planting and growing vegetables.", "Mr. Sanchez does not like classical music.", "Mrs. Sanchez cooks the vegetables that Mr. Sanchez grows.", "Mrs. Sanchez enjoys reading nineteenth century novels."], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Georgia is older than her cousin Marsha. Marsha"s brother Bart is older than Georgia. When Marsha and Bart are visiting with Georgia, all three like to play a game of Monopoly. Marsha wins more often than Georgia does.", "options": ["When he plays Monopoly with Marsha and Georgia, Bart often loses.", "Of the three, Georgia is the oldest.", "Georgia hates to lose at Monopoly.", "Of the three, Marsha is the youngest."], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Sara lives in a large city on the East Coast. Her younger cousin Marlee lives in the Mid-west in a small town with fewer than 1,000 residents. Marlee has visited Sara several times during the past five years. In the same period of time, Sara has visited Marlee only once.", "options": ["Marlee likes Sara better than Sara likes Marlee.", "Sara thinks small towns are boring.", "Sara is older than Marlee.", "Marlee wants to move to the East Coast."], "answer": "c"}]

Logical Problems
[{"question": "Tanya is older than Eric.\nCliff is older than Tanya.\nEric is older than Cliff.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "options": ["true", "false", "uncertain"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Blueberries cost more than strawberries.\nBlueberries cost less than raspberries.\nRaspberries cost more than strawberries and blueberries.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "options": ["true", "false", "uncertain"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "All the trees in the park are flowering trees.\nSome of the trees in the park are dogwoods.\nAll dogwoods in the park are flowering trees.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "options": ["true", "false", "uncertain"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Mara runs faster than Gail.\nLily runs faster than Mara.\nGail runs faster than Lily.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "options": ["true", "false", "uncertain"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Apartments in the Riverdale Manor cost less than apartments in The Gaslight Commons.\nApartments in the Livingston Gate cost more than apartments in the The Gaslight Commons.\nOf the three apartment buildings, the Livingston Gate costs the most.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "options": ["true", "false", "uncertain"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "The Kingston Mall has more stores than the Galleria.\nThe Four Corners Mall has fewer stores than the Galleria.\nThe Kingston Mall has more stores than the Four Corners Mall.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "options": ["true", "false", "uncertain"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "All the tulips in Zoe"s garden are white.\nAll the pansies in Zoe"s garden are yellow.\nAll the flowers in Zoe"s garden are either white or yellow\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "options": ["true", "false", "uncertain"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "During the past year, Josh saw more movies than Stephen.\nStephen saw fewer movies than Darren.\nDarren saw more movies than Josh.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "options": ["true", "false", "uncertain"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Rover weighs less than Fido.\nRover weighs more than Boomer.\nOf the three dogs, Boomer weighs the least.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "options": ["true", "false", "uncertain"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "All the offices on the 9th floor have wall-to-wall carpeting.\nNo wall-to-wall carpeting is pink.\nNone of the offices on the 9th floor has pink wall-to-wall carpeting.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "options": ["true", "false", "uncertain"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Class A has a higher enrollment than Class B.\nClass C has a lower enrollment than Class B.\nClass A has a lower enrollment than Class C.\nIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is", "options": ["true", "false", "uncertain"], "answer": "b"}]

Logical Games
[{"question": "Senators from urban areas are very concerned about assuring that there will be funding for a new international airport. Senators from rural areas refuse to fund anything until money for agricultural subsidies is appropriated. If the legislature funds these two programs, on which of the following could they spend the rest of the money?", "options": ["the school music program and national radio", "hurricane preparedness", "harbor improvements and the school music program", "small business loan program", "national radio and senate office building remodeling"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "If the legislature decides to fund the agricultural subsidy program, national radio, and the small business loan program, what two other programs could they fund?", "options": ["harbor improvements and international airport", "harbor improvements and school music program", "hurricane preparedness and school music program", "hurricane preparedness and international airport", "harbor improvements and hurricane preparedness"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "If the legislature decides to fund the agricultural subsidy program, national radio, and the small business loan program, the only other single program that can be funded is", "options": ["hurricane preparedness.", "harbor improvements.", "school music program.", "senate office building remodeling.", "international airport."], "answer": "d"}]

Analyzing Arguments
[{"question": "One New York publisher has estimated that 50,000 to 60,000 people in the United States want an anthology that includes the complete works of William Shakespeare. And what accounts for this renewed interest in Shakespeare? As scholars point out, his psychological insights into both male and female characters are amazing even today.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that", "options": ["Shakespeare"s characters are more interesting than fictional characters today.", "people even today are interested in Shakespeare"s work because of the characters.", "academic scholars are putting together an anthology of Shakespeare"s work.", "New Yorkers have a renewed interested in the work of Shakespeare.", "Shakespeare was a psychiatrist as well as a playwright."], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "One of the warmest winters on record has put consumers in the mood to spend money. Spending is likely to be the strongest in thirteen years. During the month of February, sales of existing single-family homes hit an annual record rate of 4.75 million.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that", "options": ["consumer spending will be higher thirteen years from now than it is today.", "more people buy houses in the month of February than in any other month.", "during the winter months, the prices of single-family homes are the lowest.", "there were about 4 million homes for sale during the month of February.", "warm winter weather is likely to affect the rate of home sales."], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Generation Xers are those people born roughly between 1965 and 1981. As employees, Generation Xers tend to be more challenged when they can carry out tasks independently. This makes Generation Xers the most entrepreneurial generation in history.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that Generation Xers", "options": ["work harder than people from other generations.", "have a tendency to be self-directed workers", "have an interest in making history", "tend to work in jobs that require risk-taking behavior.", "like to challenge their bosses work attitudes."], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "If you"re a fitness walker, there is no need for a commute to a health club. Your neighborhood can be your health club. You don"t need a lot of fancy equipment to get a good workout either. All you need is a well-designed pair of athletic shoes.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that", "options": ["fitness walking is a better form of exercise than weight lifting.", "a membership in a health club is a poor investment.", "walking outdoors provides a better workout than walking indoors.", "fitness walking is a convenient and valuable form of exercise.", "poorly designed athletic shoes can cause major foot injuries."], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "In the past, consumers would rarely walk into an ice cream store and order low-fat ice cream. But that isn"t the case today. An increasing health consciousness combined with a much bigger selection of tasty low-fat foods in all categories has made low-fat ice cream a very profitable item for ice cream store owners.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that", "options": ["low-fat ice cream produces more revenue than other low-fat foods.", "ice cream store owners would be better off carrying only low-fat ice cream.", "ice cream store owners no longer think that low-fat ice cream is an unpopular item.", "low-fat ice cream is more popular than other kinds of ice cream.", "consumers are fickle and it is impossible to please them"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Today"s high school students spend too much time thinking about trivial and distracting matters such as fashion. Additionally, they often dress inappropriately on school grounds. Rather than spending time writing another detailed dress policy, we should make school uniforms mandatory. If students were required to wear uniforms, it would increase a sense of community and harmony in our schools and it would instill a sense of discipline in our students. Another positive effect would be that teachers and administrators would no longer have to act as clothing police, freeing them up to focus on more important issues.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that", "options": ["inappropriate clothing leads to failing grades.", "students who wear school uniforms get into better colleges.", "teachers and administrators spend at least 25% of their time enforcing the dress code.", "students are not interested in being part of a community", "school uniforms should be compulsory for high school students."], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "The criminal justice system needs to change. The system could be more just if it allowed victims the opportunity to confront the person who has harmed them. Also, mediation between victims and their offenders would give the offenders a chance to apologize for the harm they have done.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that victims of a crime should", "options": ["learn to forgive their offenders.", "have the right to confront their offenders.", "learn the art of mediation.", "insist that their offenders be punished.", "have the right to impose a sentence on their offenders."], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "A few states in this country are considering legislation that would prohibit schools from using calculators before the sixth grade. Other states take a different position. Some states are insisting on the purchase of graphing calculators for every student in middle school.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that in this country", "options": ["there are at least two opinions about the use of calculators in schools.", "calculators are frequently a detriment to learning math.", "state legislators are more involved in education than ever before.", "the price of graphing calculators is less when schools buy in bulk.", "the argument against calculators in schools is unfounded."], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Today"s workforce has a new set of social values. Ten years ago, a manager who was offered a promotion in a distant city would not have questioned the move. Today, a manager in that same situation might choose family happiness instead of career advancement.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that", "options": ["most managers are not loyal to the corporations for which they work.", "businesses today do not understand their employees needs.", "employees social values have changed over the past ten years.", "career advancement is not important to today"s business managers.", "companies should require their employees to accept promotions."], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "It is well known that the world urgently needs adequate distribution of food, so that everyone gets enough. Adequate distribution of medicine is just as urgent. Medical expertise and medical supplies need to be redistributed throughout the world so that people in emerging nations will have proper medical care.\nThis paragraph best supports the statement that", "options": ["the majority of the people in the world have never been seen by a doctor.", "food production in emerging nations has slowed during the past several years.", "most of the world"s doctors are selfish about giving time and money to the poor.", "the medical-supply industry should step up production of its products.", "many people who live in emerging nations are not receiving proper medical care"], "answer": "e"}]

Statement and Assumption
[{"question": "Statement: "You are hereby appointed as a programmer with a probation period of one year and your performance will be reviewed at the end of the period for confirmation." - A line in an appointment letter.\nAssumptions:\nThe performance of an individual generally is not known at the time of appointment offer.\nGenerally an individual tries to prove his worth in the probation period.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: It is desirable to put the child in school at the age of 5 or so.\nAssumptions:\nAt that age the child reaches appropriate level of development and is ready to learn.\nThe schools do not admit children after six years of age.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: "In order to bring punctuality in our office, we must provide conveyance allowance to our employees." - In charge of a company tells Personnel Manager.\nAssumptions:\nConveyance allowance will not help in bringing punctuality.\nDiscipline and reward should always go hand in hand.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Unemployment allowance should be given to all unemployed Indian youth above 18 years of age.\nAssumptions:\nThere are unemployed youth in India who needs monetary support.\nThe government has sufficient funds to provide allowance to all unemployed youth.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: "If you trouble me, I will slap you." - A mother warns her child.\nAssumptions:\nWith the warning, the child may stop troubling her.\nAll children are basically naughty.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: The State government has decided to appoint four thousand primary school teachers during the next financial year.\nAssumptions:\nThere are enough schools in the state to accommodate four thousand additional primary school teachers.\nThe eligible candidates may not be interested to apply as the government may not finally appoint such a large number of primary school teachers.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: A warning in a train compartment - "To stop train, pull chain. Penalty for improper use Rs. 500."\nAssumptions:\nSome people misuse the alarm chain.\nOn certain occasions, people may want to stop a running train.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: If it is easy to become an engineer, I don"t want to be an engineer.\nAssumptions:\nAn individual aspires to be professional.\nOne desires to achieve a thing which is hard earned.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: The concession in rail fares for the journey to hill stations has been cancelled because it is not needed for people who can spend their holidays there.\nAssumptions:\nRailways should give concession only to needy persons.\nRailways should not encourage people to spend their holidays at hill stations.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: "The bridge was built at the cost of Rs. 128 crores and even civil bus service is not utilizing it, what a pity to see it grossly underutilized." - A citizen\"s view on a new flyover linking east and west sides of a suburb.\nAssumptions:\nThe building of such bridges does not serve any public objective.\nThere has to be some accountability and utility of money spent on public projects.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: The Government has decided to levy 2 percent on the tax amount payable for funding drought relief programmes.\nAssumptions:\nThe Government does not have sufficient money to fund drought relief programmes.\nThe amount collected by way of surcharge may be adequate to fund these drought relief programmes.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: Detergents should be used to clean clothes.\nAssumptions:\nDetergents form more lather.\nDetergents help to dislodge grease and dirt.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: It will be a substantial achievement in the field of education if one provides one school for every village in our country and enforce attendance.\nAssumptions:\nChildren in villages do not attend school regularly.\nProviding school to every village is desirable.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: The government has decided to disinvest large chunk of its equity in select public sector undertakings for a better fiscal management.\nAssumptions:\nThe amount generated out of the disinvestment process may reduce substantially the mounting fiscal deficits.\nThere will be enough demand in the market for the shares of these undertakings.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Never before such a lucid book was available on the topic.\nAssumptions:\nSome other books were available on this topic.\nYou can write lucid books on very few topics.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Please do not use lift while going down - an instruction on the top floor of a five-storey building.\nAssumptions:\nWhile going down, the lift is unable to carry any load.\nProvision of lift is a matter of facility and not of right.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: "I have not received telephone bills for nine months inspite of several complaints" - A telephone customer\"s letter to the editor of a daily\nAssumptions:\nEvery customer has a right to get bills regularly from the telephone company.\nThe customer\"s complaints point to defect in the services which are expected to be corrected.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: "This drink can be had either as it is, or after adding ice to it." - An advertisement.\nAssumptions:\nPeople differ in their preferences.\nSome people will get attracted to the drink as it can be had as it is.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: Government has permitted unaided colleges to increase their fees.\nAssumptions:\nUnaided colleges are in financial difficulties.\nAided colleges do not need to increase fees.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Be humble even after being victorious.\nAssumptions:\nMany people are humble after being victorious.\nGenerally people are not humble.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: The government has decided to pay compensation to the tune of Rs. 1 lakh to the family members of those who are killed in railway accidents.\nAssumptions:\nThe government has enough funds to meet the expenses due to compensation.\nThere may be reduction in incidents of railway accidents in near future.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Films have become indispensable for the entertainment of people.\nAssumptions:\nFilms are the only media of entertainment.\nPeople enjoy films.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Of all the newspapers published in Mumbai, readership of the "Times" is the largest in the Metropolis.\nAssumptions:\n\"Times\" is not popular in mofussil areas.\n\"Times\" has the popular feature of cartoons on burning social and political issues.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statement: Apart from the entertainment value of television, its educational value cannot be ignored.\nAssumptions:\nPeople take television to be a means of entertainment only.\nThe educational value of television is not realised properly.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: Children are influenced more by their teachers nowadays.\nAssumptions:\nThe children consider teachers as their models.\nA large amount of children"s time is spent in school.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: You know that your suit is excellent when people ask about your tailor who tailored the suit.\nAssumptions:\nPeople do not ask about your tailor if your suit is not good.\nThe people want to know the criterion of an excellent suit.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: His recent investment in the shares of Company A is only a gamble.\nAssumptions:\nHe may incur loss on his investment.\nHe may gain from his investment.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statement: Why don"t you go to the court if the employer does not pay you the Provident Fund contribution?\nAssumptions:\nCourts can intervene in matters of dispute between employer and employees.\nIt is obligatory for the employer to pay the Provident Fund contribution to the employees.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: "Double your money in five months." - An advertisement.\nAssumptions:\nThe assurance is not genuine.\nPeople want their money to grow.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: The education of a student at collegiate level, not taking into account maintenance expenses, costs four hundred rupees a year. Collegiate education is thus drawing heavily upon the national resources of an impoverished community. So college education should be restricted to a brilliant few.\nAssumptions:\nOur resources are very limited.\nOnly a few students should be admitted to the colleges.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: A\"s advice to B - "Go to Jammu via Amritsar - the shortest route".\nAssumptions:\nB wishes to go to Jammu.\nA gives advice to everybody.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: All existing inequalities can be reduced, if not utterly eradicated, by action of governments or by revolutionary change of government.\nAssumptions:\nInequality is a man-made phenomenon.\nNo person would voluntarily part with what he possesses.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: The campaign of "Keep your city clean" started by the Civil Council did not evoke any response from the citizens.\nAssumptions:\nPeople do not desire to keep their city clean.\nThe Civil Council has failed in its campaign.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: The district administration has issued a circular to all the farmers under its jurisdiction advising them for not using pesticides indiscriminately as it may pollute the ground water.\nAssumptions:\nPeople may stop using ground water if the farmers continue to use pesticides indiscriminately.\nFarmers may refrain from using pesticides indiscriminately.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: The coffee powder of company X is quite better in taste than the much advertised coffee of company Y.\nAssumptions:\nIf your product is not good, your spend more on advertisement.\nSome people are tempted to buy a product by the advertisement.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Of all the radio sets manufactured in India, the "X" brand has the largest sale.\nAssumptions:\nThe sale of all the radio sets manufactured in India is known.\nThe manufacturing of no other radio set in India is as large as "X" brand radio.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: "You should not grant him leave in this week due to exigency of work." - A supervisor advises the administrative officer.\nAssumptions:\nRequest for leave can be turned down also.\nThe supervisor has reviewed the work required to be done during the said period.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: Like a mad man, I decided to follow him.\nAssumptions:\nI am not a mad man.\nI am a mad man.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statement: The first step in treating addicts is to re-establish their lost ties, for which a continuous personal attention should be paid to the addicts under treatment.\nAssumptions:\nAddicts under treatment respond better when shown personal interest.\nAddiction and strained relationships are intimately connected.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: Beware of dogs, our dogs do not bark, but they are trained to distinguish between genuine guests and intruders.\nAssumptions:\nBarking dogs bite rarely.\nOur dogs could be dangerous for intruders.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Because of the large number of potholes in road X, reaching airport in time has become difficult.\nAssumptions:\nReaching airport in time may not be always necessary.\nThere is no other convenient road to the airport.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Safety and health practices in many Indian companies are well below the international standards.\nAssumptions:\nInternational standards of health and safety are ideal and unrealistic.\nIndian organizations do not consider safety and health management as their prime social responsibility.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Greater public participation results in good civic governance. - Statement of Municipal Commissioner of City A.\nAssumptions:\nThe municipal office is not competent to effect good civic administration.\nGood civic governance is a matter of collective will and effort of the people and administration.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: The regulatory authority has set up a review committee to find out the reasons for unstable stock prices.\nAssumptions:\nThe investors may regain confidence in stock market by this decision.\nThe review committee has the expertise to find out the causes for volatility in the stock market.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: Please note that the company will provide accommodation to only outside candidates if selected." - A condition in an advertisement.\nAssumptions:\nThe local candidates would be having some other arrangement for their stay.\nThe company plans to select only local candidates.", "options": ["Only assumption I is implicit", "Only assumption II is implicit", "Either I or II is implicit", "Neither I nor II is implicit", "Both I and II are implicit"], "answer": "a"}]

Course of Action
[{"question": "Statement: A large number of people in ward X of the city are diagnosed to be suffering from a fatal malaria type.\nCourses of Action:\nThe city municipal authority should take immediate steps to carry out extensive fumigation in ward X.\nThe people in the area should be advised to take steps to avoid mosquito bites.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: Severe drought is reported to have set in several parts of the country.\nCourses of Action:\nGovernment should immediately make arrangement for providing financial assistance to those affected.\nFood, water and fodder should immediately be sent to all these areas to save the people and cattle.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Since its launching in 1981, Vayudoot has so far accumulated losses amounting to Rs 153 crore.\nCourses of Action:\nVayudoot should be directed to reduce wasteful expenditure and to increase passenger fare.\nAn amount of about Rs 300 crore should be provided to Vayudoot to make the airliner economically viable.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Exporters in the capital are alleging that commercial banks are violating a Reserve Bank of India directive to operate a post shipment export credit denominated in foreign currency at international rates from January this year.\nCourses of Action:\nThe officers concerned in the commercial banks are to be suspended.\nThe RBI should be asked to stop giving such directives to commercial banks.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statement: A large number of people die every year due to drinking polluted water during the summer.\nCourses of Action:\nThe government should make adequate arrangements to provide safe drinking water to all its citizens.\nThe people should be educated about the dangers of drinking polluted water.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: Most of those who study in premier engineering colleges in India migrate to developed nations for better prospects in their professional pursuits.\nCourses of Action:\nAll the students joining these colleges should be asked to sign a bond at the time of admission to the effect that they will remain in India at least for ten years after they complete education.\nAll those students who desire to settle in the developed nations should be asked to pay entire cost of their education which the government subsidises.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: There is an unprecedented increase in migration of villagers to urban areas as repeated crop failure has put them into precarious financial situation.\nCourses of Action:\nThe villagers should be provided with alternate source of income in their villages which will make them stay put.\nThe migrated villagers should be provided with jobs in the urban areas to help them survive.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: As stated in the recent census report the female to male ratio is alarmingly low.\nCourses of Action:\nThe government should conduct another census to verify the results.\nThe government should immediately issue orders to all the departments to encourage people to improve the ratio.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Four districts in State A have been experiencing severe drought for the last three years resulting into exodus of people from these districts.\nCourses of Action:\nThe government should immediately start food for work programme in the district to put a halt to the exodus.\nThe government should make since efforts to provide drinking/potable water to these districts", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: If the retired Professors of the same Institutes are also invited to deliberate on restructuring of the organisation, their contribution may be beneficial to the Institute.\nCourses of Action:\nManagement may seek opinion of the employees before calling retired professors.\nManagement should involve experienced people for the systematic restructuring of the organisation.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: The sale of a particular product has gone down considerably causing great concern to the company.\nCourses of Action:\nThe company should make a proper study of rival products in the market.\nThe price of the product should be reduced and quality improved.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: The Asian Development Bank has approved a $285 million loan to finance a project to construct coal ports by Paradip and Madras Port Trusts.\nCourses of Action:\nIndia should use financial assistance from other international financial organisations to develop such ports in other places.\nIndia should not seek such financial assistance from the international financial agencies.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Doordarshan is concerned about the quality of its programmes particularly in view of stiff competition it is facing from STAR and other satellite TV channels and is contemplating various measures to attract talent for its programmes.\nCourses of Action:\nIn an effort to attract talent, the Doordarshan has decided to revise its fee structure for the artists.\nThe fee structure should not be revised until other electronic media also revise it.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: The Minister said that the teachers are still not familiarised with the need, importance and meaning of population education in the higher education system. They are not even clearly aware about their role and responsibilities in the population education programme.\nCourses of Action:\nPopulation education programme should be included in the college curriculum.\nOrientation programme should be conducted for teachers on population education", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: A recent study shows that children below five die in the cities of the developing countries mainly from diarrhoea and parasitic intestinal worms.\nCourses of Action:\nGovernments of the developing countries should take adequate measures to improve the hygienic conditions in the cities.\nChildren below five years in the cities of the developing countries need to be kept under periodic medical check-up.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: The kharif crops have been affected by the insects for consecutive three years in the district and the farmers harvested less than fifty percent of produce during these years.\nCourses of Action:\nThe farmers should seek measures to control the attack of insects to protect their crops next year.\nThe Government should increase the support price of kharif crops considerably to protect the economic interests of farmers.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: The car dealer found that there was a tremendous response for the new XYZ"s car-booking with long queues of people complaining about the duration of business hours and arrangements.\nCourses of Action:\nPeople should make their arrangement of lunch and snacks while going for car XYZ"s booking and be ready to spend several hours.\nArrangement should be made for more booking desks and increased business hours to serve more people in less time.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: The State Government has decided to declare "Kala Azar" as a notifiable disease under the Epidemics Act. Family members or neighbours of the patient are liable to be punished in case they did not inform the State authorities.\nCourses of Action:\nEfforts should be made to effectively implement the Act.\nThe cases of punishment should be propagated through mass media so that more people become aware of the stern actions.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: The Chairman stressed the need for making education system more flexible and regretted that the curriculum has not been revised in keeping with the pace of the changes taking place.\nCourses of Action:\nCurriculum should be reviewed and revised periodically.\nSystem of education should be made more flexible.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: The Central Bureau of Investigation receives the complaint of an officer taking bribe to do the duty he is supposed to.\nCourses of Action:\nCBI should try to catch the officer red-handed and then take a strict action against him.\nCBI should wait for some more complaints about the officer to be sure about the matter.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: The Indian electronic component industry venturing into the West European markets faces tough competition from the Japanese.\nCourses of Action:\nIndia should search for other international markets for its products.\nIndia should improve the quality of the electronic components to compete with the Japanese in capturing these markets.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Orissa and Andhra Pradesh have agreed in principle to set up a joint control board for better control, management and productivity of several inter-state multipurpose projects.\nCourses of Action:\nOther neighbouring states should set up such control boards.\nThe proposed control board should not be allowed to function as such joint boards are always ineffective.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: The Government has decided not to provide financial support to voluntary organisations from next Five Year Plan and has communicated that all such organisations should raise funds to meet their financial needs.\nCourses of Action:\nVoluntary organisations should collaborate with foreign agencies.\nThey should explore other sources of financial support.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: The availability of imported fruits has increased in the indigenous market and so the demand for indigenous fruits has been decreased.\nCourses of Action:\nTo help the indigenous producers of fruits, the Government should impose high import duty on these fruits, even if these are not of good quality.\nThe fruit vendors should stop selling imported fruits. So that the demand for indigenous fruits would be increased.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statement: There has been an unprecedented increase in the number of successful candidates in this year"s School Leaving Certificate Examination.\nCourses of Action:\nThe government should make arrangements to increase number of seats of intermediate courses in existing colleges.\nThe government should take active steps to open new colleges to accommodate all these successful candidates.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: On an average, about twenty people are run over by trains and die every day while crossing the railway tracks through the level crossing.\nCourses of Action:\nThe railway authorities should be instructed to close all the level crossings.\nThose who are found crossing the tracks, when the gates are closed, should be fined heavily", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Majority of the students in many schools do not pass in the final examination.\nCourses of Action:\nThese schools should be closed down as these have become unproductive.\nThe teachers of these schools should immediately be retrenched.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statement: In spite of the Principal"s repeated warnings, a child was caught exploding crackers secretly in the school.\nCourses of Action:\nAll the crackers should be taken away from the child and he should be threatened not to do it again.\nThe child should be severely punished for his wrong act.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: It is necessary to adopt suitable measures to prevent repetition of bad debts by learning from the past experiences of mounting non-performing assets of banks.\nCourses of Action:\nBefore granting loan to customers their eligibility for loan should be evaluated strictly.\nTo ensure the payment of instalments of loan, the work, for which loan was granted, should be supervised minutely on regular basis.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: A very large number of students have failed in the final high school examination due to faulty questions in one of the subjects.\nCourses of Action:\nAll the students who have failed in the subject should be allowed to take supplementary examination.\nAll those who are responsible for the error should be suspended and an enquiry should be initiated to find out the facts.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: A large number of engineering graduates in the country are not in a position to have gainful employment at present and the number of such engineers is likely to grow in the future.\nCourses of Action:\nThe government should launch attractive employment generation schemes and encourage these graduates to opt for such schemes to use their expertise and knowledge effectively.\nThis happened due to proliferation of engineering colleges in the country and thereby lowered the quality of the engineering graduates. Those colleges which are not equipped to impart quality education should be closed down.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Every year, at the beginning or at the end of the monsoons, we have some cases of conjunctivitis, but this year, it seems to be a major epidemic, witnessed after nearly four years.\nCourses of Action:\nPrecautionary measures should be taken after every four years to check this epidemic.\nPeople should be advised to drink boiled water during rainy season.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Every year large number of devotees dies due to severe cold on their way to the shrine located at the top of the mountain range.\nCourses of Action:\nThe devotees should be discouraged to visit the shrine without having proper warm clothes and other amenities.\nThe government should provide warm clothes and shelter to all the devotees visiting the shrine.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: There has been an unprecedented increase in the number of requests for berths in most of the long distance trains during the current holiday season.\nCourses of Action:\nThe railway authority should immediately increase the capacity in each of these trains by attaching additional coaches.\nThe people seeking accommodation should be advised to make their travel plan after the holiday.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: The Finance Minister submits his resignation a month before the new budget is to be presented in the Parliament.\nCourses of Action:\nThe resignation should be accepted and another person should be appointed as the Finance Minister.\nThe resignation should not be accepted.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: A large number of people visiting India from country X have been tested positive for carrying viruses of a killer disease.\nCourses of Action:\nThe government of India should immediately put a complete ban on people coming to India from country X including those Indians who are settled in country X.\nThe government of India should immediately set up detection centres at all its airports and seaports to identify and quarantine those who are tested positive.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: There has been less than forty percent voter turnout in the recent assembly elections.\nCourses of Action:\nThe election commission should cancel the entire election process as the votes cast are not adequate to represent people.\nThe election commission should take away the voting rights of those who did not exercise their rights.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statement: Most of the development plans develop in papers only.\nCourses of Action:\nThe in-charges should be instructed to supervise the field-work regularly.\nThe supply of paper to such departments should be cut short.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: The vegetable traders feel that the prices of onion will again go up shortly in the State "P"\nCourses of Action:\nThe "P" State Government should purchase and store sufficient quantity of onion in advance to control prices.\nThe "F" State Government should make available network of fair price shops for the sale of onions during the period of shortage.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: It is reported that though Vitamin E present in fresh fruits and vegetables is beneficial for human body, capsule Vitamin E does not have the same effect on human body.\nCourses of Action:\nThe sale of capsule Vitamin E should be banned.\nPeople should be encouraged to take fresh fruits and vegetables to meet the body"s requirement of Vitamin E.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Youngsters are often found staring at obscene posters.\nCourses of Action:\nChildren should be punished and penalized if they are found doing so.\nAny display of such material should be banned.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: One of the problems facing the food processing industry is the irregular supply of raw material. The producers of raw material are not getting a reasonable price.\nCourses of Action:\nThe government should regulate the supply of raw material to other industries also.\nThe government should announce an attractive package to ensure regular supply of raw material for food processing industry.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: The Committee has criticized the Institute for its failure to implement a dozen of regular programmes despite an increase in the staff strength and not drawing up a firm action plan for studies and research.\nCourses of Action:\nThe broad objectives of the Institute should be redefined to implement a practical action plan.\nThe Institute should give a report on reasons for not having implemented the planned programmes.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: India has been continuously experiencing military threats from its neighbouring countries.\nCourses of Action:\nIndia should engage into an all out war to stop the nagging threats.\nIndia should get the neighbours into a serious dialogue to reduce the tension at its borders.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: As many as ten coaches of a passenger train have derailed and blocked both pairs of the railway tracks.\nCourses of Action:\nThe railway authorities should immediately send men and equipment to the spot to clear the railway tracks.\nAll the trains running in both the directions should be diverted to other routes.", "options": ["Only I follows", "Only II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}]

Statement and Conclusion
[{"question": "Statements: In a one day cricket match, the total runs made by a team were 200. Out of these 160 runs were made by spinners.\nConclusions:\n80% of the team consists of spinners.\nThe opening batsmen were spinners.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: The old order changed yielding place to new.\nConclusions:\nChange is the law of nature.\nDiscard old ideas because they are old.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: Government has spoiled many top ranking financial institutions by appointing bureaucrats as Directors of these institutions.\nConclusions:\nGovernment should appoint Directors of the financial institutes taking into consideration the expertise of the person in the area of finance.\nThe Director of the financial institute should have expertise commensurate with the financial work carried out by the institute.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: Population increase coupled with depleting resources is going to be the scenario of many developing countries in days to come.\nConclusions:\nThe population of developing countries will not continue to increase in future.\nIt will be very difficult for the governments of developing countries to provide its people decent quality of life.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements: Prime age school-going children in urban India have now become avid as well as more regular viewers of television, even in households without a TV. As a result there has been an alarming decline in the extent of readership of newspapers.\nConclusions:\nMethod of increasing the readership of newspapers should be devised.\nA team of experts should be sent to other countries to study the impact of TV. on the readership of newspapers.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: In Japan, the incidence of stomach cancer is very high, while that of bowel cancer is very low. But Japanese immigrate to Hawaii, this is reversed - the rate of bowel cancer increases but the rate of stomach cancer is reduced in the next generation. All this is related to nutrition - the diets of Japanese in Hawaii are different than those in Japan.\nConclusions:\nThe same diet as in Hawaii should be propagated in Japan also.\nBowel cancer is less severe than stomach cancer.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: The Government run company had asked its employees to declare their income and assets but it has been strongly resisted by employees union and no employee is going to declare his income.\nConclusions:\nThe employees of this company do not seem to have any additional undisclosed income besides their salary.\nThe employees union wants all senior officers to declare their income first.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: Monitoring has become an integral part in the planning of social development programmes. It is recommended that Management Information System be developed for all programmes. This is likely to give a feedback on the performance of the functionaries and the efficacy with which services are being delivered.\nConclusions:\nAll the social development programmes should be evaluated.\nThere is a need to monitor the performance of workers.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: The T.V. programmes, telecast specially for women are packed with a variety of recipes and household hints. A major portion of magazines for women also contains the items mentioned above.\nConclusions:\nWomen are not interested in other things.\nAn average woman"s primary interest lies in home and specially in the kitchen.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements: The distance of 900 km by road between Bombay and Jafra will be reduced to 280 km by sea. This will lead to a saving of Rs. 7.92 crores per annum on fuel.\nConclusions:\nTransportation by sea is cheaper than that by road.\nFuel must be saved to the greatest extent", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements: The manager humiliated Sachin in the presence of his colleagues.\nConclusions:\nThe manager did not like Sachin.\nSachin was not popular with his colleagues.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: Women"s organisations in India have welcomed the amendment of the Industrial Employment Rules 1946 to curb sexual harassment at the work place.\nConclusions:\nSexual harassment of women at work place is more prevalent in India as compared to other developed countries.\nMany organisations in India will stop recruiting women to avoid such problems.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: Nation X faced growing international opposition for its decision to explode eight nuclear weapons at its test site.\nConclusions:\nThe citizens of the nation favoured the decision.\nSome powerful countries do not want other nations to become as powerful as they are.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: In a highly centralised power structure, in which even senior cabinet ministers are prepared to reduce themselves to pathetic countries or yesmen airing views that are primarily intended to anticipate or reflect the Prime Minister"s own performances, there can be no place for any consensus that is quite different from real or contrived unanimity of opinion, expressed through a well orchestrated endorsement of the leader"s actions.\nConclusions:\nThe Ministers play safe by not giving anti-government views.\nThe Prime Minister does not encourage his colleagues to render their own views.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: National Aluminium Company has moved India from a position of shortage to self-sufficiency in the metal.\nConclusions:\nPreviously, India had to import aluminium.\nWith this speed, it can soon become a foreign exchange earner.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: Jade plant has thick leaves and it requires little water.\nConclusions:\nAll plants with thick leaves require little water.\nJade plants may be grown in places where water is not in abundance.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements: Use "Kraft" colours. They add colour to our life. - An advertisement.\nConclusions:\nCatchy slogans do not attract people.\nPeople like dark colours.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: All those political prisoners were released on bail who had gone to jail for reasons other than political dharnas. Bail was not granted to persons involved in murders.\nConclusions:\nNo political - prisoner had committed murder.\nSome politicians were not arrested.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: Modern man influences his destiny by the choice he makes unlike in the past.\nConclusions:\nEarlier there were fewer options available to man.\nThere was no desire in the past to influence the destiny.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: Water supply in wards A and B of the city will be affected by about 50% on Friday because repairing work of the main lines is to be carried out.\nConclusions:\nThe residents in these wards should economise on water on Friday.\nThe residents in these wards should store some water on the previous day.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: People who speak too much against dowry are those who had taken it themselves.\nConclusions:\nIt is easier said than done.\nPeople have double standards.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: The national norm is 100 beds per thousand populations but in this state, 150 beds per thousand are available in the hospitals.\nConclusions:\nOur national norm is appropriate.\nThe state"s health system is taking adequate care in this regard.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements: Our securities investments carry market risk. Consult your investment advisor or agent before investing.\nConclusions:\nOne should not invest in securities.\nThe investment advisor calculates the market risk with certainty.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements: Money plays a vital role in politics.\nConclusions:\nThe poor can never become politicians.\nAll the rich men take part in politics.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: Vegetable prices are soaring in the market.\nConclusions:\nVegetables are becoming a rare commodity.\nPeople cannot eat vegetables.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: The serious accident in which a person was run down by a car yesterday had again focused attention on the most unsatisfactory state of roads.\nConclusions:\nThe accident that occurred was fatal.\nSeveral accidents have so far taken place because of unsatisfactory state of roads.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: In a recent survey report, it has been stated that those who undertake physical exercise for at least half an hour a day are less prone to have any heart ailments.\nConclusions:\nModerate level of physical exercise is necessary for leading a healthy life.\nAll people who do desk-bound jobs definitely suffer from heart ailments.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: A bird in hand is worth two in the bush.\nConclusions:\nWe should be content with what we have.\nWe should not crave for what is not.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: This world is neither good nor evil; each man manufactures a world for himself.\nConclusions:\nSome people find this world quite good.\nSome people find this world quite bad.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: The eligibility for admission to the course is minimum second class Master"s degree. However, the candidates who have appeared for the final year examination of Master"s degree can also apply.\nConclusions:\nAll candidates who have yet to get their Master"s degree will be there in the list of selected candidates.\nAll candidates having obtained second class Master"s degree will be there in the list of selected candidates.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: Any student who does not behave properly while in the school brings bad name to himself and also for the school.\nConclusions:\nSuch student should be removed from the school.\nStricter discipline does not improve behaviour of the students.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: A Corporate General Manager asked four managers to either submit their resignations by the next day or face termination orders from service. Three of them had submitted their resignations by that evening.\nConclusions:\nThe next day, the remaining manager would also resign.\nThe General Manager would terminate his services the next day.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statements: Only good singers are invited in the conference. No one without sweet voice is a good singer.\nConclusions:\nAll invited singers in the conference have sweet voice.\nThose singers who do not have sweet voice are not invited in the conference.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: To cultivate interest in reading, the school has made it compulsory from June this year for each student to read two books per week and submit a weekly report on the books.\nConclusions:\nInterest in reading can be created by force.\nSome students will eventually develop interest in reading.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements: Applications of applicants who do no fulfil eligibility criteria and/or who do not submit applications before last date will be summarily rejected and will not be called for the written test.\nConclusions:\nThose who are called for the written test are those who fulfil eligibility criteria and have submitted their applications before last date.\nWritten test will be held only after scrutiny of applications.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: Recent trends also indicate that the number of child migrants in large cities is increasing. These children leave their families to join the ranks of urban poor doing odd jobs in markets, workshops, hotels or in service sectors.\nConclusions:\nMigration to big cities should be checked.\nThe plight of poor children should be thoroughly studied.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: No country is absolutely self-dependent these days.\nConclusions:\nIt is impossible to grow and produce all that a country needs.\nCountrymen in general have become lazy.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: The percentage of the national income shared by the top 10 per cent of households in India is 35.\nConclusions:\nWhen an economy grows fast, concentration of wealth in certain pockets of population takes place.\nThe national income is unevenly distributed in India.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements: Players who break various records in a fair way get special prizes. Player X broke the world record but was found to be under the influence of a prohibited drug.\nConclusions:\nX will get the special prize.\nX will not get the special prize.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements: Company X has marketed the product. Go ahead; purchase it if price and quality are your considerations.\nConclusions:\nThe product must be good in quality.\nThe price of the product must be reasonable.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: Quality has a price tag. India is allocating lots of funds to education.\nConclusions:\nQuality of education in India would improve soon.\nFunding alone can enhance quality of education.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: Although we have rating agencies like Crisil, ICRA, there is demand to have a separate rating agency for IT companies to protect investors.\nConclusions:\nAssessment of financial worth of IT companies calls for separate set of skills, insight and competencies.\nNow the investors investing in IT companies will get protection of their investment.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: The standard of education in private schools is much better than Municipal and Zila Parishad-run schools.\nConclusions:\nThe Municipal and Zila Pariskad should make serious efforts to improve standard of their schools.\nAll Municipal and Zila Parishad schools should be closed immediately.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: All the organised persons find time for rest. Sunita, in spite of her very busy schedule, finds time for rest.\nConclusions:\nSunita is an organised person.\nSunita is an industrious person.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: Domestic demand has been increasing faster than the production of indigenous crude oil.\nConclusions:\nCrude oil must be imported.\nDomestic demand should be reduced.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "c"}]

Theme Detection
[{"question": "The attainment of individual and organisational goals is mutually interdependent and linked by a common denominator - employee work motivation. Organisational members are motivated to satisfy their personal goals, and they contribute their efforts to the attainment of organisational objectives as means of achieving these personal goals.\n\nThe passage best supports the statement that motivation -", "options": ["encourages an individual to give priority to personal goals over organisational goals.", "is crucial for the survival of an individual and organisation.", "is the product of an individual"s physical and mental energy.", "is the external force which induces an individual to contribute his efforts.", "makes organisation and society inseparable."], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Due to enormous profits involved in smuggling, hundreds of persons have been attracted towards this anti-national activity. Some of them became millionaires overnight. India has a vast coastline both on the Eastern and Western Coast. It has been a heaven for smugglers who have been carrying on their activities with great impunity. There is no doubt, that from time to time certain seizures were made by the enforcement authorities, during raids and ambush but even allowing these losses the smugglers made huge profits.\n\nThe passage best supports the statement that", "options": ["smuggling hampers the economic development of a nation.", "smuggling ought to be curbed.", "authorities are taking strict measures to curb smuggling.", "smuggling is fast increasing in our country owing to the quick profit it entails."], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Though the waste of time or the expenditure on fashions is very large, yet fashions have come to stay. They will not go, come what may. However, what is now required is that strong efforts should be made to displace the excessive craze for fashion from the minds of these youngsters.\n\nThe passage best supports the statement that:", "options": ["fashion is the need of the day.", "the excessive craze for fashion is detrimental to one"s personality.", "the hoard for fashion should be done away with so as not to let down the constructive development.", "work and other activities should be valued more than the outward appearance."], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "One of the important humanitarian by-products of technology is the greater dignity and value that it imparts to human labour. In a highly industrialized society, there is no essential difference between Brahmin and Dalit, Muslim and Hindu; they are equally useful and hence equally valuable for in the industrial society individual productivity fixes the size of the pay cheque and this fixes social status.\n\nThe passage best supports the statement that:", "options": ["technology decides individual"s social status.", "castes and religions are man-made.", "human labour has dignity and value.", "all individuals, irrespective of caste and creed, are born equal.", "industrial society is a great leveller of men."], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "The future of women in India is quite bright and let us hope that they will justify their abilities by rising to the occasion. Napoleon was right when he declared that by educating the women we can educate the whole nation. Because a country can never rise without the contribution of 50% of their population.\n\nThe passage best supports the statement that:", "options": ["India is striving hard for the emancipation of women.", "all women should be well educated.", "a nation can progress only when women are given equal rights and opportunities as men.", "women ought to be imparted full freedom to prove their worth and contribute to the progress of the nation."], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "The prevention of accidents makes it necessary not only that safety devices be used to guard exposed machinery but also that mechanics be instructed in safety rules which they must follow for their own protection, and that lighting in the plant be adequate.\n\nThe passage best supports the statement that industrial accidents -", "options": ["are always avoidable;", "may be due to ignorance.", "cannot be entirely overcome.", "can be eliminated with the help of safety rules.", "usually result from inadequate machinery."], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "To forgive an injury is often considered to be a sign of weakness; it is really a sign of strength. It is easy to allow oneself to be carried away by resentment and hate into an act of vengeance; but it takes a strong character to restrain those natural passions. The man who forgives an injury proves himself to be the superior of the man who wronged himself and puts the wrong-doer to shame.\n\nThe passage best supports" the statement that:", "options": ["the sufferer alone knows the intensity of his sufferings.", "people tend to forgive the things happened in the past.", "natural passions are difficult to suppress.", "mercy is the noblest form of revenge.", "a person with calm and composed nature has depth of thought and vision."], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Industrial exhibitions play a major role in a country"s economy. Such exhibitions, now regularly held in Delhi, enable us to measure the extent of our own less advanced industrial progress and the mighty industrial power and progress of countries like the U.K., U.S.A. and Russia whose pavilions are the centres of the greatest attention and attractions.\n\nThe passage best supports the statement that industrial exhibitions -", "options": ["greatly tax the poor economies.", "are more useful for the developed countries like U.S.A. whose products stand out superior to those of the developing countries.", "are not of much use to the countries who are industrially backward.", "boost up production qualitatively and quantitatively by analytical comparison of a country"s products with those of the developed countries."], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "The school has always been the most important means of transferring the wealth of tradition form one generation to the next. This applies today in an even higher degree than in former times for, through the modern development of economy, the family as bearer of tradition and education has become weakened.\n\nThis passage best supports the statement that for transferring the wealth of tradition from one generation to the next -", "options": ["there are means other than the school.", "several different sources must be tried.", "economic development plays a crucial role", "modern technology must be put to use.", "family, as ever, is the most potent means."], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Emerson said that the poet was landlord, Sealord, airlord. The flight of imagination made the poet master of land, sea and air. But a poet"s dream of yesterday becomes today an actual achievement and a reality for all men. Even those who invented, improved and perfected the aeroplane could hardly have dreamt of the possibility of flight into outer space.\n\nThe passage best supports the statement that:", "options": ["seemingly impossible imaginations make one a good poet,", "all imaginations become a reality some day.", "what man imagined has never been impossible; he has always turned it a reality through his conception of ideas and sheer hard labour.", "man has reached the climax of technological development with his exploration into outer space."], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "It is up to our government and planners to devise ways and means for the mobilisation of about ten crore workers whose families total up about forty crore men, women and children. Our agriculture is over-manned. A lesser number of agriculturists would mean more purchasing or spending power to every agriculturist. This will result in the shortage of man-power for many commodities to be produced for which there will be a new demand from a prosperous agrarian class. This shortage will be removed by surplus man-power released from agriculture as suggested above.\n\nThe passage best supports the statement that:", "options": ["employment in production is more fruitful than employment in agriculture.", "Indian economy is in a poor shape basically due to improper mobilisation of man-power.", "a shift of labour from agricultural sector to the industrial sector would uplift the living standard.", "the industrial sector is labour-deficient while the agricultural sector is over-manned in our country."], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Exports and imports, a swelling favourable balance of trade, investments and bank-balances, are not an index or a balance sheet of national prosperity. Till the beginning of the Second World War, English exports were noticeably greater than what they are today. And yet England has greater national prosperity today than it ever had. Because the income of average Englishmen, working as field and factory labourers, clerks, policemen, petty shopkeepers and shop assistants, domestic workers and other low-paid workers, has gone up.\n\nThe passage best supports the statement that:", "options": ["a country"s economic standard can be best adjudged by per capital income.", "a country"s balance of trade is the main criteria of determining its economic prosperity.", "a nation"s economy strengthens with the increase in exports.", "English trade has continually increased since the Second World War."], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Satisfaction with co-workers, promotion opportunities, the nature of work, and pay goes with high performance among those with strong growth needs. Among those with weak growth needs, no such relationship is present - and, in fact, satisfaction with promotion opportunities goes with low performance.\n\nThis passage best supports the statement that:", "options": ["satisfaction is an inevitable organisational variable.", "job satisfaction and performance are directly and closely related.", "relationship between job satisfaction and performance is moderated by growth need.", "every organisation has few employees having weak growth need.", "high performance is essential for organisational effectiveness."], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "The only true education comes through the stimulation of the child"s powers by the demands of the social situations in which he finds himself. Through these demands he is stimulated to act as a member of a unity, to emerge from his original narrowness of action and feeling, and to conceive himself from the standpoint of the welfare of the group to which he belongs.\n\nThe passage best supports the statement that real education -", "options": ["will take place if the children imbibe action and feeling.", "will take place if the children are physically strong.", "is not provided in our schools today.", "comes through the interaction with social situations.", "comes from the self-centred approach of the students."], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "The press should not be afraid of upholding and supporting a just and righteous cause. It should not be afraid of criticising the government in a healthy manner. The press has to be eternally vigilant to protect the rights of the workers, backward and suppressed sections of the society. It should also give a balanced view of the things so that people can be helped in the formation of a healthy public opinion.\n\nThe passage best supports the statement that", "options": ["press has a great role to play in a democracy.", "the press is the only means to project to the masses the policies of the government.", "the freedom of press is essential for the proper functioning of democracy.", "the press can be used by the governments as an effective media for the upliftment of the backward sections of society.", "all the information given by the press should be well-articulated so as to gain a good opinion towards the ruling party."], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Throughout the ages the businessman has helped build civilisation"s great cities, provided people with luxuries and artists with patronage, and lift his fellow citizens to understand the standard of living. In the last few centuries the businessman has seeded the Industrial Revolution around the world.\n\nThe passage best supports the statement that the businessman -", "options": ["is accountable to the society.", "lives luxurious and comfortable life.", "is the beneficiary of the Industrial Revolution.", "is capable of raising his standard of living.", "has contributed to the growth of civilisation."], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "There is a shift in our economy from a manufacturing to a service orientation. The increase in service-sector will require the managers to work more with people rather than with objects and things from the assembly line.\n\nThis passage best supports the statement that:", "options": ["managers should have a balanced mind.", "assembly line will exist in service organisations.", "interpersonal skills will become more important in the future work place.", "manufacturing organisations ignore importance of people.", "service organisations will not deal with objects and things."], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "The virtue of art does not allow the work to be interfered with or immediately ruled by anything other than itself. It insists that it alone shall touch the work in order to bring it into being. Art requires that nothing shall attain the work except through art itself.\n\nThis passage best supports the statement that:", "options": ["art is governed by external rules and conditions.", "art is for the sake of art and life.", "art is for the sake of art alone.", "artist realises his dreams through his artistic creation.", "artist should use his art for the sake of society."], "answer": "c"}]

Cause and Effect
[{"question": "Statements:\nThe prices of petrol and diesel in the domestic market have remained unchanged for the past few months.\nThe crude oil prices in the international market have gone up substantially in the last few months.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe government has recently fixed the fees for professional courses offered by the unaided institutions which are much lower than the fees charged last year.\nThe parents of the aspiring students launched a severe agitation last year protesting against the high fees charged by the unaided institutions.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe Reserve Bank of India has recently put restrictions on few small banks in the country.\nThe small banks in the private and co-operative sector in India are not in a position to withstand the competitions of the bigger in the public sector.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements:\nAll the schools in the area had to be kept closed for most part of the week.\nMany parents have withdrawn their children from the local schools.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements:\nIndia has surpassed the value of tea exports this year over all the earlier years due to an increase in demand for quality tea in the European market.\nThere is an increase in demand of coffee in the domestic market during the last two years.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThere is unprecedented increase in the number of young unemployed in comparison to the previous year.\nA large number of candidates submitted applications against an advertisement for the post of manager issued by a bank.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe police authority has recently caught a group of house breakers.\nThe citizens group in the locality have started night vigil in the area.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements:\nMajority of the students in the college expressed their opinion against the college authority"s decision to break away from the university and become autonomous.\nThe university authorities have expressed their inability to provide grants to its constituent colleges.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe literacy rate in the district has been increasing for the last four years.\nThe district administration has conducted extensive training programme for the workers involved in the literacy drive.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe school authority has asked the X Std. students to attend special classes to be conducted on Sundays.\nThe parents of the X Std. students have withdrawn their wards from attending private tuitions conducted on Sundays.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe Government has imported large quantities of sugar as per trade agreement with other countries.\nThe prices of sugar in the domestic market have fallen sharply in the recent months.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThere is sharp decline in the production of oil seeds this year.\nThe Government has decided to increase the import quantum of edible oil.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe private medical colleges have increased the tuition fees in the current year by 200 per cent over the last year"s fees to meet the expenses.\nThe Government medical colleges have not increased their fees in spite of price escalation.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statements:\nLarge number of people living in the low-lying areas has been evacuated during the last few days to safer places.\nThe Government has rushed in relief supplies to the people living in the affected areas.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements:\nIt is the aim of the city"s civic authority to get the air pollution reduced by 20% in the next two months.\nThe number of asthma cases in the city is constantly increasing.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe local co-operative credit society has decided to stop giving loans to farmers with immediate effect.\nA large number of credit society members have withdrawn major part of their deposits from the credit society.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe employees of the biggest bank in the country have given an indefinite strike call starting from third of the next month.\nThe employees of the Central Government have withdrawn their week long demonstrations.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements:\nPolice resorted to lathi-charge to disperse the unlawful gathering of large number of people.\nThe citizens" forum called a general strike in protest against the police atrocities.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements:\nMajority of the citizens in the locality belongs to higher income group.\nThe sales in the local super market are comparatively much higher than in other localities.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe life today is too fast, demanding and full of variety in all aspects which at times leads to stressful situations.\nNumber of suicide cases among teenagers is on increase.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe government has decided to make all the information related to primary education available to the general public.\nIn the past, the general public did not have access to all these information related to primary education.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe farmers have decided against selling their kharif crops to the Government agencies.\nThe Government has reduced the procurement price of kharif crops starting from last month to the next six months.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe performance of most of the students in final exam of class X in the schools run by the Government was excellent.\nMany teachers of the Government schools left the school and joined private schools.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThere is considerable reduction in the number of people affected by water-borne diseases in City A during this rainy season.\nThe government has opened four new civil hospitals in City A in the beginning of the year.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe prices of vegetables have been increased considerably during this summer.\nThere is tremendous increase in the temperature during this summer thereby damaging crops greatly.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThere has been a high increase in the incidents of atrocities against women in the city during the past few months.\nThe police authority has been unable to nab the culprits who are committing crime against women.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statements:\nRural and semi-urban areas in the country have been suffering due to load shedding for quite some time.\nIf the Government is not able to overcome the power crisis, load shedding will be extended even to the urban areas.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThe university authority has instructed all the colleges under its jurisdiction to ban use of all phones inside the college premises.\nMajority of the teachers of the colleges signed a joint petition to the university complaining the disturbances caused by cell phone ring-tones inside the classrooms.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements:\nMost of the steel producing companies in the country have made considerable profit during the last financial year.\nMany Asian countries have been importing huge quantities of steel from India.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements:\nThere is increase in water level of all the water tanks supplying drinking water to the city during the last fortnight.\nMost of the trains were cancelled last week due to water-logging on the tracks.", "options": ["Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect", "Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect", "Both the statements I and II are independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes", "Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause"], "answer": "e"}]

Statement and Argument
[{"question": "Statement: Should India encourage exports, when most things are insufficient for internal use itself?\nArguments:\nYes. We have to earn foreign exchange to pay for our imports.\nNo. Even selective encouragement would lead to shortages.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Should all the drugs patented and manufactured in Western countries be first tried out on sample basis before giving licence for sale to general public in India?\nArguments:\nYes. Many such drugs require different doses and duration for Indian population and hence it is necessary.\nNo. This is just not feasible and hence cannot be implemented.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Should India make efforts to harness solar energy to fulfil its energy requirements?\nArguments:\nYes, Most of the energy sources used at present is exhaustible.\nNo. Harnessing solar energy requires a lot of capital, which India lacks in.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be students union in college/university?\nArguments:\nNo. This will create a political atmosphere in the campus.\nYes, it is very necessary Students are future political leaders.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: Should India give away Kashmir to Pakistan?\nArguments:\nNo. Kashmir is a beautiful state. It earns a lot of foreign exchange for India.\nYes. This would help settle conflicts.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Should cottage industries be encouraged in rural areas?\nArguments:\nYes. Rural people are creative.\nYes. This would help to solve the problem of unemployment to some extent.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Should young entrepreneurs be encouraged?\nArguments:\nYes. They will help in industrial development of the country.\nYes. They will reduce the burden on employment market.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: Should all the annual examinations up to Std. V be abolished?\nArguments:\nYes. The young students should not be burdened with such examinations which hampers their natural growth.\nNo. The students will not study seriously as they will get automatic promotion to the next class and this will affect them in future.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: Should Indian scientists working abroad be called back to India?\nArguments:\nYes. They must serve the motherland first and forget about discoveries, honours, facilities and all.\nNo. We have enough talent; let them stay where they want.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statement: Should we scrap the system of formal education beyond graduation?\nArguments:\nYes. It will mean taking employment at an early date.\nNo. It will mean lack of depth of knowledge.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be an upper age limit of 65 years for contesting Parliamentary/ Legislative Assembly elections?\nArguments:\nYes. Generally, people above the age of 65 lose their dynamism and will power.\nNo. The life span is so increased that people remain physically and mentally active even up to the age of 80.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statement: Should new big industries be started in Mumbai?\nArguments:\nYes. It will create job opportunities.\nNo. It will further add to the pollution of the city.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statement: Should high chimneys be installed in industries?\nArguments:\nYes. It reduces pollution at ground level.\nNo. It increases pollution in upper atmosphere.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Does India need so many plans for development?\nArguments:\nYes. Nothing can be achieved without proper planning.\nNo. Too much time, money and energy is wasted on planning.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Should articles of only deserving authors be allowed to be published?\nArguments:\nYes. It will save a lot of paper which is in short supply.\nNo. It is not possible to draw a line between the deserving and the undeserving.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Should colleges be given the status of a university in India?\nArguments:\nYes. Colleges are in a better position to assess the student"s performance and therefore the degrees will be more valid.\nNo. It is Utopian to think that there will not be nepotism and corruption in awarding degrees by colleges.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statement: Should the prestigious people who have committed crime unknowingly, be met with special treatment?\nArguments:\nYes. The prestigious people do not commit crime intentionally.\nNo. It is our policy that everybody is equal before the law.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Can pollution be controlled?\nArguments:\nYes. If everyone realizes the hazards it may create and cooperates to get rid of it, pollution may be controlled.\nNo. The crowded highways, factories and industries and an ever-growing population eager to acquire more and more land for constructing houses are beyond control.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statement: Should the railways in India be privatized in a phased manner like other public sector enterprises?\nArguments:\nYes. This is the only way to bring in competitiveness and provide better services to the public.\nNo. This will pose a threat to the national security of our country as multinationals will enter into the fray.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statement: Should internal assessment in colleges be abolished?\nArguments:\nYes. This will help in reducing the possibility of favouritism.\nNo, teaching faculty will lose control over students.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Should all the unauthorized structures in the city be demolished?\nArguments:\nNo. Where will the people residing in such houses live?\nYes. This will give a clear message to general public and they will refrain from constructing unauthorized buildings.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be a maximum limit for the number of ministers in the Central Government?\nArguments:\nNo. The political party in power should have the freedom to decide the number of ministers to be appointed.\nYes. The number of ministers should be restricted to a certain percentage of the total number of seats in the parliament to avoid unnecessary expenditure.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Should foreign films be banned in India?\nArguments:\nYes. They depict an alien culture which adversely affects our values.\nNo. Foreign films are of a high artistic standard.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statement: Is buying things on instalments profitable to the customer?\nArguments:\nYes. He has to pay less.\nNo, paying instalments upsets the family budget.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statement: Should Doordarshan be given autonomous status?\nArguments:\nYes. It will help Doordarshan to have fair and impartial coverage of all important events.\nNo. The coverage of events will be decided by a few who may not have healthy outlook.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Should adult education programme be given priority over compulsory education programme?\nArguments:\nNo. It will also help in success of compulsory education programme.\nYes. It will help to eliminate the adult illiteracy.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Should new universities be established in India?\nArguments:\nNo. We have still not achieved the target for literacy.\nNo. We will have to face the problem of unemployed but highly qualified people.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: Should non-vegetarian food be totally banned in our country?\nArguments:\nYes. It is expensive and therefore it is beyond the means of most people in our country.\nNo. Nothing should be banned in a democratic country like ours.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Should a total ban be put on trapping wild animals?\nArguments:\nYes. Trappers are making a lot of money;\nNo. Bans on hunting and trapping are not effective.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statement: Should Government close down loss-making public sector enterprises?\nArguments:\nNo. All employees will lose their jobs, security and earning, what would they do?\nYes. In a competitive world the rule is "survival of the fittest".", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Should government jobs in rural areas have more incentives?\nArguments:\nYes. Incentives are essential for attracting government servants there.\nNo. Rural areas are already cheaper, healthier and less complex than big cities. So ? Why offer extra incentives!", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be a cap on maximum number of contestants for parliamentary elections in any constituency?\nArguments:\nYes. This will make the parliamentary elections more meaningful as the voters can make a considered judgement for casting their vote.\nNo. In a democracy any person fulfilling the eligibility criteria can contest parliamentary elections and there should be no restrictions.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: Should so much money be spent on advertisements?\nArguments:\nYes. It is an essential concomitant in a capitalist economy.\nNo. It leads to wastage of resources.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Should all the legislators be forced to resign from their profession?\nArguments:\nYes. They will be able to devote more time for the country.\nNo, nobody will contest election.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Should "computer knowledge" be made a compulsory subject for all the students at secondary school level?\nArguments:\nNo, our need is "bread" for everyone, we cannot follow western models.\nYes. We cannot compete in the international market without equipping our children with computers.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be uniforms for students in the colleges in India as in the schools?\nArguments:\nYes, this will improve the ambience of the colleges as all the students will be decently dressed.\nNo. The college students should not be regimented and they should be left to choose their clothes for coming to the college.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Should India engage into a dialogue with neighbouring countries to stop cross border tension?\nArguments:\nYes. This is the only way to reduce the cross border terrorism and stop loss of innocent lives.\nNo. Neighbouring countries cannot be relied upon in such matters, they may still engage in subversive activities.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be a world government?\nArguments:\nYes. It will help in eliminating tensions among the nations.\nNo. Then, only the developed countries will dominate in the government.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Should the practice of transfers of clerical cadre employees from government offices of one city to those of another be stopped?\nArguments:\nNo. Transfer of employees is a routine administrative matter and we must continue it.\nYes. It involves lot of governmental expenditure and inconvenience too many compared to the benefits it yields.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statement: Is paying ransom or agreeing to the conditions of kidnappers of political figures, a proper course of action?\nArguments:\nYes. The victims must be saved at all cost.\nNo. It encourages the kidnappers to continue their sinister activities.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statement: Should religion be banned?\nArguments:\nYes. It develops fanaticism in people.\nNo, Religion binds people together.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statement: Should India become a permanent member of UN"s Security Council?\nArguments:\nYes. India has emerged as a country which loves peace and amity.\nNo. Let us first solve problems of our own people like poverty, malnutrition.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statement: Should fashionable dresses be banned?\nArguments:\nYes. Fashions keep changing and hence consumption of cloth increases.\nNo. Fashionable clothes are a person"s self expression and therefore his/her fundamental right.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Should an organization like UNO be dissolved?\nArguments:\nYes. With cold war coming to an end, such organizations have no role to play\nNo, In the absence of such organizations there may be a world war.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statement: Should there be no place of interview in selection?\nArguments:\nYes, it is very subjective in assessment.\nNo. It is the only instrument to judge candidates" motives and personality.", "options": ["Only argument I is strong", "Only argument II is strong", "Either I or II is strong", "Neither I nor II is strong", "Both I and II are strong"], "answer": "a"}]

Logical Deduction
[{"question": "Statements: No women teacher can play. Some women teachers are athletes.\nConclusions:\nMale athletes can play.\nSome athletes can play.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: All bags are cakes. All lamps are cakes.\nConclusions:\nSome lamps are bags.\nNo lamp is bag.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statements: All mangoes are golden in colour. No golden-coloured things are cheap.\nConclusions:\nAll mangoes are cheap.\nGolden-coloured mangoes are not cheap.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements: Some kings are queens. All queens are beautiful.\nConclusions:\nAll kings are beautiful.\nAll queens are kings.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: Some doctors are fools. Some fools are rich.\nConclusions:\nSome doctors are rich\nSome rich are doctors.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: All roads are waters. Some waters are boats.\nConclusions:\nSome boats are roads.\nAll waters are boats.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: No bat is ball. No ball is wicket.\nConclusions:\nNo bat is wicket.\nAll wickets are bats.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: All flowers are trees. No fruit is tree.\nConclusions:\nNo fruit is flower.\nSome trees are flowers.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: Every minister is a student. Every student is inexperienced.\nConclusions:\nEvery minister is inexperienced.\nSome inexperienced are students.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: All roads are poles. No pole is a house.\nConclusions:\nSome roads are houses.\nSome houses are poles.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: All fish are tortoise. No tortoise is a crocodile.\nConclusions:\nNo crocodile is a fish.\nNo fish is a crocodile.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: Some dedicated souls are angels. All social workers are angels.\nConclusions:\nSome dedicated souls are social workers.\nSome social workers are dedicated souls.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: No gentleman is poor. All gentlemen are rich.\nConclusions:\nNo poor man is rich.\nNo rich man is poor.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: Some swords are sharp. All swords are rusty\nConclusions:\nSome rusty things are sharp.\nSome rusty things are not sharp.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: All fishes are grey in colour. Some fishes are heavy.\nConclusions:\nAll heavy fishes are grey in colour.\nAll light fishes are not grey in colour.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: All good athletes win. All good athletes eat well.\nConclusions:\nAll those who eat well are good athletes.\nAll those who win eat well.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: All film stars are playback singers. All film directors are film stars.\nConclusions:\nAll film directors are playback singers.\nSome film stars are film directors.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: All hill stations have a sun-set point. X is a hill station.\nConclusions:\nX has a sun-set point.\nPlaces other than hill stations do not have sun-set points.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: Some dreams are nights. Some nights are days.\nConclusions:\nAll days are either nights or dreams.\nSome days are nights.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements: All jungles are tigers. Some tigers are horses.\nConclusions:\nSome horses are jungles.\nNo horse is jungle.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statements: All poles are guns. Some boats are not poles.\nConclusions:\nAll guns are boats.\nSome boats are not guns.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: Many scooters are trucks. All trucks are trains.\nConclusions:\nSome scooters are trains.\nNo truck is a scooter.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: Some papers are pens. Angle is a paper.\nConclusions:\nAngle is not a pen.\nAngle is a pen.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statements: All birds are tall. Some tall are hens.\nConclusions:\nSome birds are hens.\nSome hens are tall.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements: Some papers are pens. Some pencils are pens.\nConclusions:\nSome pens are pencils.\nSome pens are papers.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: Some men are educated. Educated persons prefer small families.\nConclusions:\nAll small families are educated.\nSome men prefer small families.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements: All educated people read newspapers. Rahul does not read newspaper.\nConclusions:\nRahul is not educated.\nReading newspaper is not essential to be educated.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: All pens are chalks. All chairs are chalks.\nConclusions:\nSome pens are chairs.\nSome chalks are pens.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements: Bureaucrats marry only intelligent girls. Tanya is very intelligent.\nConclusions:\nTanya will marry a bureaucrat.\nTanya will not marry a bureaucrat.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statements: Some engineers are fools. Anand is an engineer.\nConclusions:\nSome fools are engineers.\nAnand is a fool.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: All windows are doors. No door is wall.\nConclusions:\nNo window is wall.\nNo wall is door.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: Most teachers are boys. Some boys are students.\nConclusions:\nSome students are boys.\nSome teachers are students.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: No man is a donkey. Rahul is a man.\nConclusions:\nRahul is not a donkey.\nAll men are not Rahul.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: Some books are pens. No pen is pencil.\nConclusions:\nSome books are pencils.\nNo book is pencil.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statements: All men are married. Some men are educated.\nConclusions:\nSome married are educated.\nSome educated are married.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: All tubes are handles. All cups are handles.\nConclusions:\nAll cups are tubes.\nSome handles are not cups.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: No magazine is cap. All caps are cameras.\nConclusions:\nNo camera is magazine.\nSome cameras are magazines.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statements: All huts are mansions. All mansions are temples.\nConclusions:\nSome temples are huts.\nSome temples are mansions.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: Some books are tables. Some tables are mirrors.\nConclusions:\nSome mirrors are books.\nNo book is mirror.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "c"}, {"question": "Statements: All trucks fly. Some scooters fly.\nConclusions:\nAll trucks are scooters.\nSome scooters do not fly.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: Raman is always successful. No fool is always successful.\nConclusions:\nRaman is a fool.\nRaman is not a fool.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "b"}, {"question": "Statements: Some desks are caps. No cap is red.\nConclusions:\nSome caps are desks.\nNo desk is red.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}, {"question": "Statements: Some hens are cows. All cows are horses.\nConclusions:\nSome horses are hens.\nSome hens are horses.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "e"}, {"question": "Statements: All water is divine. All temples are divine.\nConclusions:\nAll water is temple.\nAll temples are water.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "d"}, {"question": "Statements: All men are dogs. All dogs are cats.\nConclusions:\nAll men are cats.\nAll cats are men.", "options": ["Only conclusion I follows", "Only conclusion II follows", "Either I or II follows", "Neither I nor II follows", "Both I and II follow"], "answer": "a"}]
